Guide to the Richard Scowcroft Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Richard Scowcroft papers
1939-1993
SC0585
Scowcroft, Richard.
Scowcroft, Richard
6 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Richard Scowcroft, March 2000
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Biography
Richard Scowcroft joined the faculty of the Department of English at Stanford in 1947; he was appointed Professor in 1957 and retired in 1979. He served as associate director and then director of the Creative Writing Program and was chair of the English department from 1976 to 1978. He did his undergraduate work at the University of Utah and then traveled for two years before pursuing graduate work at Harvard. He was a teaching fellow there from 1942-46, earned his Ph.D. in 1946, and was a Briggs-Copeland instructor, 1946-47. In addition to editing numerous textbooks and story anthologies, he has published six novels.
Scope and Content
The papers of Richard Scowcroft, 1939-1993, document his teaching and writing career and include letters from writers, editors, and colleagues; Stanford teaching materials and departmental files; speeches and lectures; and manuscripts, typescripts, and reviews of his novels. There is a sizeable amount of correspondence from Tillie Olsen, 1959-73, Wallace Stegner, 1944-73, Jessamyn West, 1948-1983; his editors Carolyn Blakemore, Paul Brooks, and Dorothy De Santillana; and his agent Henry Volkening. Other correspondents include Bruce Bliven, Tom Bontly, Bliss Carnochan, John Cheever, Avis De Voto, Maxwell Geismar, Helen Howe, Janet Lewis, John L'Heureux, Erika Mann, Theodore Morrison, Anais Nin, Katherine Anne Porter, May Sarton, and Stephen Spender.
His class files contain two types of materials: reading lists, exams, and other handouts; and his lectures or lecture notes. Folder titles were taken from Scowcroft's original folders and in some cases there is overlap with other classes, especially if the content is similar. The collection also includes manuscripts of stories written while at Harvard and an unpublished novel, three photographs, and an audio tape of Scowcroft reading from his novel First Family.
Access Terms
Bauer, Todd.; Bliven, Bruce, 1889-1977; Bontly, Thomas,, 1939-; Brooks, Paul,, 1909-1998.; Carnochan, W. B.; Cheever, John.; De Santillana, Dorothy.; De Voto, Avis.; Geismar, Maxwell David,, 1909-; Howe, Helen.; Jones, Richard,, 1926 July 25-; L'Heureux, John.; Lewis, Janet, 1899-1998; Mann, Erika,, 1905-1969.; Morrison, Theodore, 1901-1988.; Nin, Anaïs, 1903-1977; Olsen, Tillie.; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980.; Sarton, May,, 1912-1995.; Spender, Stephen,, 1909-1995.; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Stanford University. Creative Writing Program; Stanford University. Department of English.; Stegner, Wallace Earle, 1909-1993; Turow, Scott.; Volkening, Henry.; West, Jessamyn.; Creative writing--Study and teaching.; English literature--Study and teaching.; Manuscripts (for publication).
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1944-1993; Series 1
  - Abrahams, William, 1955, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Berman, Sylvia, 1950-70 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blakemore, Carolyn, (includes copies of correspondence with Jessamyn West), 1966-71 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brooks, Paul, 1944-54 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cheever, John, 1975-77 and undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cowley, Malcolm and Muriel, 1956-81 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - De Santillana, Dorothy, 1954-73 and undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Geismar, Maxwell, 1946-53 and undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Griffith, Corinne, 1950-52 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Howe, Helen, 1945-69 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lewis, Janet, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - L'Heureux, John, 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Morrison, Theodore, 1945-73 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Nin, Anais, 1947 and undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Olsen, Tillie, 1959-61 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Olsen, Tillie, (with photographs), 1962-63 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Olsen, Tillie, note and typescript of her seminar "Death of the Creative Process,", 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Olsen, Tillie, 1964-65 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Olsen, Tillie, 1966-68 Jan (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Olsen, Tillie, letter (with pressed leaves), 7-Oct-68 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Olsen, Tillie, 1969-73 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Olsen, Tillie, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pember, Timothy, 1953 and undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Richardson, Stewart, 1965-66 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sarton, May, 1951-57 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Stegner, Mary, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Stegner, Wallace, 1944-50 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Stegner, Wallace, 1959-62 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Stegner, Wallace, 1965-73 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Stewart, Donald, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Turow, Scott, 1987-88 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Volkening, Henry, 1948-64 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Volkening, Henry, 1965-72 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Walton, Jon, 1966-67 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - West, Jessamyn, 1948-49 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - West, Jessamyn, 1952-54 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - West, Jessamyn, 1959-61 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - West, Jessamyn, 1962-63 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - West, Jessamyn, 1964-66 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - West, Jessamyn, 1967-69 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - West, Jessamyn, 1970-78 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - West, Jessamyn, 1980-83 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - West, Jessamyn, Christmas notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - West, Jessamyn, fragment and undated letters (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - West, Jessamyn, clippings and photograph (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, A - B (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, C - D (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, E - J (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, L - M (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, N - P (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, R - S (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, T - Z (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, no last name (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Jones, Richard, 1969-1971 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Jones, Richard, 1972-1974 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Jones, Richard, 1975-1976 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Jones, Richard, 1977-1979 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Jones, Richard, 1980-1982 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Jones, Richard, 1983-1985 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Jones, Richard, 1986-1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Jones, Richard, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Jones, Richard, 1990-1992 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Jones, Richard, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Jones, Richard, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Jones, Richard, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Jones, Richard, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Jones, Richard, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Jones, Richard, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Jones, Richard, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Jones, Richard, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Jones, Richard, undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Scowcroft to Jones, 1969-1972 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Scowcroft to Jones, 1973-1978 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Scowcroft to Jones, 1980-1985 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Scowcroft to Jones, 1986-1988 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Scowcroft to Jones, 1990-2000 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Scowcroft to Jones (Christmas letters), undated (Box 14, Folder 24)
- Stanford University Administrative and Teaching Files, 1949-1978; Series 2
  - Departmental correspondence, 1960-78 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Departmental memos, 1976-78 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - List of fellowships (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Ph.D. reading lists and qualifying exams, 1952-75 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ph.D. oral exams, individuals A - O (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ph.D. oral exams, individuals P - Z (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - English 30 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - English 75 (Introduction to the Novel), notes and lectures [some materials may also related to Eng. 30] (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - English 75, lecture notes, etc. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - English 75, exams, reading lists, etc., 1949-70 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - English 173, lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - English 173, exams, reading lists, etc., 1955-70 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - English 198 (Development of the Short Story) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - English 241, lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - English 241, lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - English 241, exams, reading lists, etc. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - English 242 (The English Novel in the 19th Century) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - English 255, lecture (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - English 307A, lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - English 307A, class materials, book orders (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Freshman English, sources (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Writing classes, lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Writing classes, lecture notes (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Writing classes, sources (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Speeches, Series 3
  - Two speeches: on his novel First Family; and on another of his novels (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Two speeches: on the Stanford creative writing center; and on his Stanford colleagues (?) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Two speeches: on teaching the novel (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Three speeches: the writer as a teacher of creative writing; speech to instructors; and on teaching writing (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Three speeches: on writing; why write it?; and why I write (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - One speech: on novels and novelists (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Two speeches: the novel is an act of communication; and in search of a novel (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Two speeches: discussion of the novel in terms of family; and remarks on the novel (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Two speeches: on modern fiction; and the heroine in 20th century fiction (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Two speeches: Ivanhoe 1820; and on the 19th century novel (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Two speeches: techniques of fiction; and the circle, or how to return to where you started from (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - One speech: the young writer and his material; and a set of "Play-a-Plot" plot cards with instructions (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - One speech: Carleton miscellany (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous notes for speeches (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Writings, 1939-1973; Series 4
  - Harvard class stories, 1939-40
    - "Career" (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - "Death of Cleo" (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "The Derelict" (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "The Last Summer" (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "Ship for Singapore" (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "The Spirit of the Thing" (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "A Story of a Lady" (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Children of the Covenant (published in, 1945)
    - Manuscript, unnumbered part and chapter 7 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Manuscript, parts XI and XII (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Manuscript, parts XIV and XV (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Manuscript, parts XVI and XVII (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Manuscript, parts IXX, XX, and unnumbered (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Manuscript, unnumbered sections (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Manuscript, unnumbered sections (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Manuscript, part XII, chapter 7, and unnumbered section (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Manuscript, part X and unnumbered section (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Manuscript, part IV and chapter 6 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Synopsis (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, chapters 1-3 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, chapters 4-8 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, chapters 9-12 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, chapters 13-16 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Typescript, chapters 17 - end (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, prologue (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Typescript, chapters 1 (incomplete) and 5 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Letter from Emerson C. Willey re legal research, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Announcements and listings (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Reviews, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - First Family (published in, 1950)
    - Manuscript, chapters 1-2 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Manuscript, chapters 3-4 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Manuscript, chapters 5-7 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Manuscript, chapters 8-10 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Manuscript, chapters 11-13 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Manuscript, chapters 14-16 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Manuscript, chapters 17-18 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, pages 1-80 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, pages 81-175 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, pages 176-252 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, pages 253-328 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, pages 329-428 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Ads (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Radio program scripts, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Reviews, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - A View of the Bay (published in, 1955)
    - Manuscript, chapters 1-4 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript, chapters 5-8 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript, chapters 10-11 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript, chapters 12-17 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Manuscript, chapters 6, unnumbered, and 9A (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Synopsis (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Typescript, pages 1-74 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Typescript, pages 75-145 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Typescript, pages 146-252 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Dust jackets (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Reviews, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Unpublished novel, early 1960s
    - Manuscript, chapters 1-3 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript, chapters 4-6 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript, chapters 7-9 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript, chapters 10-12 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript, chapters 13-17 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript, chapters 18 - end (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Typescript, pages 41-68, 96-111 and 115-116 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Typescript, pages 175-303 (chapters 10-17) (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Typescript, pages 304-380 (chapters 18-20) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Wherever She Goes (published in, 1967)
    - Manuscript, chapters 1-5 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript, chapters 6-8 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript, chapters 9-11 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript, chapters 12-13 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript, chapters 14 - end (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, chapters 1-6 (pages 1-74) (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Typescript, chapters 7-11 (pages 75-137) (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, chapters 12 - end (pages 138-217) (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Contract and book jacket (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Ads and reviews (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The Ordeal of Dudley Dean (published in, 1969)
    - Manuscript, chapters 1-3 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript, chapters 4-6 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript, chapters 7-9 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Manuscript, chapters 10-13 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Manuscript, chapters 14-19 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Typescript no. 1, pages 1-94 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Typescript no. 1, pages 95-187 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Typescript no. 1, pages 188-269 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Typescript no. 2, pages 1-94 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Typescript no. 2, pages 95-187 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Typescript no. 2, pages 188-269 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Letter from publisher and corrections, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Cover art (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Ads and notices (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Reviews (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Back to Fire Mountain (published in, 1973)
    - Manuscript, "Prologue" and "The First Night" (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript, "The Second Night" (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript, "The Third Night" and "The Fourth Night" (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript, "The Fifth Night" and "Epilogue" (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Typescript number 1, pages 1-85 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Typescript number 1, pages 86-165 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Typescript number 1, pages 166 - end (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Typescript number 2, pages 1-85 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Typescript number 2, pages 86-137 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Typescript number 2, pages 138-205 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - From Manuscript to Printed Book; Exhortations and advice to our authors, and rules and usage which we follow in preparing manuscripts for the press. The Atlantic Monthly Press in association with Little, Brown and Company (35 page pamphlet) (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Contract, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Reviews (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Book Reviews
    - The Novels of James Gould Cozzens by Frederick Bracher, Harcourt Brace, 1959, reviewed by Richard Scowcroft (typescript) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - The Other Side
    - Mss, Book I, Ch. 1-2 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Mss, Book I, Ch. 3-5 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Mss, Book II, Ch. 1-3 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Mss, Book II, Ch. 4-7 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Mss, Book III (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Mss, Book IV, Ch. 1-3 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Mss, Book IV, Ch. 4-5 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Mss, miscellaneous pages (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Mss, miscellaneous pages 2 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Tss, pp. 1-118 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Tss, pp. 119-276 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Tss, pp. 277-403 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Tss, pp. 404-439 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Tss, Book IV, Ch. 3-5 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Tss, incomplete, not in order (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Tss, Miscellaneous pages (1) (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Tss, Miscellaneous pages (2) (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Tss, pp. 1-105 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Tss, pp. 106-184 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Tss, pp. 185-276 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Tss, pp. 277-362 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Tss, pp. 363-442 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Passage to Illyria
    - Tss, pp. 1-82 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Tss, pp. 83-191 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Tss, pp. 192-291 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Tss, pp. 292-411 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous Papers, Series 5
  - Biographical information (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Clippings (re humor) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Stegner, Wallace, clipping (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - "White Princess," option agreement (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - R. Scowcroft reading "Babe" from First Family, 1953 Aug 19; 1 audiotape(s) (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
- Oversized Materials, Series 6
  - Galleys of Back to Fire Mountain (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Galleys of First Family (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Galleys of A View of the Bay (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Original pencil layout for ad for First Family (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper color illustration for First Family (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2002-029
  - Clippings of reviews (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings of reviews (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bauer, Todd MA Thesis, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reviews of deVoto book, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Pope and Cibber", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fire Mountain (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fire Mountain (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bread loaf writers conference, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Utah Miscellany, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, A-B, 1973-2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, C-G, 1965-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, H-J, 1948-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Richard Jones, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Kinder (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, L, 1974-1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, M-P, 1945-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, S-W (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Anti-Pamela (volume), 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notebook, quotes (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notebook (Box 2, Folder 3)